Finding Aid for Affirmative Action Office. (University of Michigan), Publications 1973-1995
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Affirmative Action Office. (University of Michigan), publications 1973-1995
University of Michigan. Affirmative Action Office.
Newsletters, brochures, reports and other material published by the University of Michigan office responsible for overseeing campus-wide affirmative action programs and policies.
02140 Bimu B29 2
3 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
Publications are received periodically from the unit. Donor 5818
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The collection is open for research.
The University of Michigan Affirmative Action Program was developed in 1972 in response to federal laws passed in the 1960s to guarantee equal opportunity in employment for women and minorities. To comply with the federal regulations, the university developed recruiting practices and set goals and timetables for achieving equality for women and minorities in employment. Since 1970, the university has issued an Annual Compliance Report to the United States Department of Health, Education and Welfare (HEW). Much of the program's work during the early 1970s revolved around preparation of these reports and interpreting HEW criteria.
Nellie M. Varner was appointed first director of the Affirmative Action Program. Varner's main responsibility was to interpret the specific guidelines that were issued in October, 1972 by the Office of Civil Rights in the Department of Health, Education and Welfare (OCR-HEW guidelines). Her task was to create a university framework to meet these guidelines. As explained in the University Record of October 16, 1972, "These new guidelines spell out methods which colleges and universities must use in complying with Federal nondiscrimination orders. They include the setting of either percentage or numerical goals for hiring women and minorities...'The major job of my office,' says Dr. Varner, 'is in working out these procedures for monitoring to see if achievement of policy is made. After identifying deficiencies constructive recommendations can be made to the executive officers.'"
The director also served as a liaison between the university, federal government officials, and the university's Commissions for Minority Affairs and Women. The commissions were established by President Robben Fleming in 1971. His charge to the commissions was to examine university policies, procedures, and practices which might contribute to discrimination against minority groups and women, and to review the Affirmative Action Program of the university and make recommendations. The commissions and the program worked together to develop procedures for affirmative action and also submitted recommendations to the president for improving programs within the university.
In 1976 the Affirmative Action Program was reorganized. The name was changed to Affirmative Action Office and the Commissions for Minority Affairs and Women were integrated with the office. The move was designed to eliminate duplication of efforts and more efficiently focus activity on the eradication of discriminatory practices. The timing for the move was also right. Gwendolyn Baker had just been appointed the new director of the Affirmative Action Office and the two commission's chairmanships were about to expire. Charles Allemand replaced Gwendolyn Baker as director of the Affirmative Action Office in 1978.
During the 1970s and 1980s, the role of the office expanded beyond the protection of women and minorities. The groups protected by nondiscrimination laws and policies grew to include individuals with handicaps, people between the ages of 40 and 70, and veterans of the Vietnam War. In addition, the list of characteristics against which institutions could not discriminate included religion, national origin, height, weight, marital status, and sexual orientation.
In 1980 Virginia Nordby became director of the Affirmative Action office. The office was divided into compliance and programs teams, with Nordby overseeing both. This division reflects the two major functions of the office, that of meeting federal affirmative action guidelines, and serving the needs of groups or individuals on campus protected by nondiscrimination laws.
According to a September, 1987 Affirmative Action Office newsletter, the compliance team is responsible for all the data retrieval, analysis, and reporting necessary for writing the reports on minority student recruitment and retention, faculty and staff employment, and affirmative action compliance required by the university and the federal government. Much of this function involves monitoring the race and gender composition of the faculty, staff, and student body; setting affirmative action goals and monitoring progress made toward achieving them; and monitoring faculty and staff recruitment (In the Affirmative, vol. 5, 1987-1988)
The program team addresses the needs of members of protected groups through grievance counseling, program development, and policy recommendations. It also provides workshops to the university community. The workshops offered include Combating Sexual Harassment; Valuing Diversity: Anti-Racism Education and Training; Stares and Stair: Achieving Attitudinal and Architectural Accessibility; Managing AIDS in the Workplace; Understanding Affirmative Action and Nondiscrimination; Recruiting and Retaining a Diversified Staff; and Managing an Aging Workforce. In 1991, the office held the first campus-wide diversity and resource forum. At the forum, people learned about the many creative programs and strategies used by different university units to make a better environment in which people of all races, creeds, and cultures, live, work, and study.
The Affirmative Action Office also works with constituency groups, which are composed of volunteers united by a common cause who are willing to work together on projects to improve the university. The office provides direct staff and financial support to such groups as the Academic Women's Caucus, the African-American Organizations Coalition, the Age Concerns Council, the Association of Black Professionals and Administrators, the Commission for Women, the Women of Color Task Force, the Men of Color Task Force, the Task Force on Sexual Orientation, and the Women's Initiative Group.
In 1988 Virginia Nordby left the Affirmative Action Office. Mary Ann Swain became the interim director. In 1989, Zaida I. Giraldo became the director. In 1992, Jimmy A. Myers took over the position as Interim Director. On February 15, 1994 the Affirmative Action Office combined with the Personnel Office to become the Office of Human Resources and Affirmative Action. Jackie McClain was appointed as the executive director.
The Publications of the Affirmative Action Office measures 3 linear feet and covers the period from 1973 to 1994. The subgroup is divided into two series: Unit Publications and Sub-Unit Publications.
Unit Publications include Minority Student Reports, Reports to the Regents and a complete run of the newsletter In the Affirmative.
Sub-Unit Publications consist of materials produced by units within the Affirmative Action Office. These include the Council for Disability Concerns and the Study Committee on the Status of Lesbians and Gay Men.
Subjects:
Affirmative action programs--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Discrimination in employment--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Administration.; University of Michigan. Affirmative Action Office.; University of Michigan. Commission for Women.; Women--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; College teachers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women college teachers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Genre/Form:
Reports.; Manuals.; Newsletters.; Brochures.
- Unit Publications
  - Historical Material 1979, 1990-1996 (Box 1)
  - Brochures
    - General 1981-1988, undated (Box 1)
    - Dr. Martin Luther King Commemorative Health Care Symposia 1985 (Box 1)
  - Catalogs
    - Media Resources for Programs on Multicultural Awareness, 1987 (Box 1)
    - Women's Resource List, July and November 1985 (Box 1)
  - Manuals
    - Discrimination and Discriminatory Harassment Policies, August and September 1988, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Getting in and Around University of Michigan Buildings: Accessibility Information for Key Buildings, undated (Box 1)
    - Policy on Discrimination and Discriminatory Harassment, 1989 (Box 1)
    - The Resource Handbook for Students with Handicaps, 1986 (Box 1)
    - Response and Procedures for Complaints of Discriminatory Harassment by Faculty and Staff in the University Environment, 1992 (Box 1)
    - Search Committees, Posting Requirements and Waivers: A Guide to the Instructional and Academic Administrative Appointment Process, 1980, 1982, 1986 (Box 1)
    - Tell Someone! A Program for Combating Sexual Harassment: Trainer's Manual, 1981 (Box 1)
    - What You Should Know about the University's Requirements for Nondiscrimination: A Handbook for Managers, Supervisors, Employees, 1992, 1993 (Box 1)
  - Maps
    - Accessibility Map, 1991 (Box 1)
  - Newsletters
    - In the Affirmative, 1983-1994, 12 folders (Box 1)
  - Proceedings
    - People and Issues in Equal Opportunity, 1981 (Box 1)
    - Public Forum on "The Future for Women at the University of Michigan,", 1988 (Box 1)
  - Reports
    - Access and Opportunities for People with Handicaps at the University of Michigan, 1986 (Box 1)
    - Affirmative Action Program, 1973, 1976-1980, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Affirmative Action Progress Report, 1973/74-1974/1975, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - An Analysis of Productivity of Nontenured Minority Faculty Based on the Faculty Cohort Studies, 1987 (Box 1)
    - Combating Sexual Harassment: Establishing a Program, 1982 (Box 1)
    - Enrollment of and Degrees Granted to Female Student: The University of Michigan, Ann Arbor 1926-1985, 1986 (Box 1)
    - Faculty Cohort Study, 1984 (Box 1)
    - The Faculty Cohort Study: College of Literature, Science and the Arts, 1987 (Box 1)
    - The Faculty Cohort Study: School of Education, 1987 (Box 2)
    - The Faculty Cohort Study: School of Medicine, 1986 (Box 2)
    - Minority Recruitment, Enrollment, Retention and Graduation, 1980 (Box 2)
    - Minority Students at the University of Michigan, 1982-1987/88, 12 folders (Box 2)
    - Report on Vietnam-Era Veterans Survey Questionnaire, 1983 (Box 2)
    - Report to the Regents
      - 1983/84-1985/86, 4 folders (Box 2)
      - 1985/86-1987/88, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Report to the University Community, 1982-1983, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Selected Sections of the Affirmative Action Report for the School of Business Administration, 1984-1985 (Box 3)
    - Title IX Self Evaluation Summary, 1976 (Box 3)
    - The University of Michigan Affirmative Action Compliance Program, 1979-1982, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - University of Michigan Replacement Hospital Project: Affirmative Action Plan, 1982 (Box 3)
    - Update 1983 Affirmative Action Report to the University Community, 1983 (Box 3)
  - Statistics
    - Faculty, Staff and Students of Color: A Statistical Profile, 1988-1991, 1992 (Box 3)
    - Faculty, Staff and Students of Color: A Statistical Profile for Academic Years 1981-82 Through 1991-92, 1992 (Box 3)
    - Faculty, Staff and Students of Color: A Statistical Profile for the Academic Years 1982-83 Through 1992-93, 1993 (Box 3)
    - Faculty, Staff and Students of Color: A Statistical Profile for the Academic Years 1983-84 Through 1993-94, 1994 (Box 3)
    - Summaries of Employment and Affirmative Action Data by EE06 Occupational Groups, 1980-1981 (Box 3)
- Sub-Unit Publications
  - Council for Disability Concerns
    - Reports
      - Ten Year Report 1983-1993, 1993 (Box 3)
      - A Report on: Learning Disabilities, 1987 (Box 3)
  - The Study Committee on the Status of Lesbians and Gay Men
    - Reports
      - From Invisibility to Inclusion: Opening the Doors for Lesbians and Gay Men at the University of Michigan, 1991 (Box 3)